# 哈喽大家好
Hello everyone
# 前几天我炒了一大锅火锅底料
A few days ago, I made a big pot of hot pot soup base
# 然后一直放着
Then it has been staying still
# 就是正好今天降温一下降了10℃度
Today, the temperature has dropped by 10 °C
# 而且还在下雨
And it’s raining now
# 所以我今天准备用这个火锅底料来再做一个火锅来吃
So today I’ll make a hot pot with the hot pot soup base
# 今天有黄鳝还有其它很多东西
We have Asian swamp eels and a lot of other stuff
# 我伯爷还从屠场拿回来的猪脑花
And also pig brains uncle brought from the slaughterhouse
# 拿了10几个猪脑花回来我们自己做
Over 10 pig brains for us to cook
# 我四伯现在教一下大家怎么弄这个（猪脑花）
Now uncle is going to show how to handle it (pig brain)
# 这个筋膜它
This silver skin is like...
# 我四伯就是放在温水里面先
Uncle first put it in warm water
# 洗一下然后拍两下最后把那个膜撕开
wash it, and then tap it, and finally tear off the silver skin
# 四伯爷是可以哦你这个（手法）
Uncle, you are skilled in it
# 是嘛那些样子都不要啊 开玩笑哦
Sure thing, not kidding!
# 我们这个脑花虽然说口感比较好
Although the texture of pig brain is good
# 但是年纪大的少吃一点
elderly people shouldn’t eat too much
# 为什么呢 因为它胆固醇非常的高
Why? Because it contains a high amount of cholesterol
# 就像那个蛋黄一样
Just like egg yolk
# 正常人一天吃2个没问题
Normal people can eat two everyday, which is fine
# 如果你吃多了的就吸收不了
If you eat too much, you can’t absorb it
# 而且还有一些副作用
And there are some side effects
# 弄这个就是要轻手轻脚的
You must be very tender to handle it
# 太重的话就烂了
If you are too rough, it breaks down
# 烂了就不好吃了
If it breaks down, it tastes bad
# 我跟我伯爷把这个脑花就清洗出来了
Uncle and I have finished washing the pig brains
# 洗了半个小时左右吧
It took us about half an hour
# 非常不好洗
Not an easy work at all
# 这里14个
We have 14 here
# 有5斤没得哦
Is there 5 jin (=2.5kg)?
# 14个可能没有
14 pig brains might not be enough
# 没有5斤
Not enough for 5 jin
# 可能3斤是少不脱的
Should be at least 3 jin, probably
# 3斤到4斤14个脑花
3 to 4 jin for 14 pig brains
# 然后选择把这个火锅底料挖一点出来
Then let’s take out some of the hot pot soup base
# 先把它划开
Slice it first
# 像切蛋糕一样
Like how you slice a cake
# 没划透底哦
Have you sliced through?
# 差不多
Yeah, should have
# 放一点宽油
Put in a bit of “kuan you” oil # 这里选择不解释宽油，因为语义上是矛盾的...
# 好
Alright
# 大家家里面没有条件自己炒火锅底料的也可以去买
If you can’t make hot pot soup base at home, you may also buy it
# 买完了之后很多人他直接放到水里面煮
Many people simply buy it and dump it into water to boil
# 当然那个样子也可以
That way is still fine
# 但是那个火锅不香
but it won’t be very flavorful
# 我们要想让它香一点还是要放点油进去
If we want it to be more flavorful, we still have to add some oil first
# 放那个辣椒花椒大蒜姜放进去爆一下
and put in some chili, Sichuan peppercorns, garlic and ginger and fry
# 最后再放火锅底料
Then put in the hot pot soup base at last
# 再放汤烧开
and add in soup stock to boil
# 烧开了之后再调味
And season it after it boils
# 这冬天吃这个火锅还比较适合噶
Hot pot is such a good fit for winter, isn’t it?
# 是嘛
Yeah
# 吃起越吃越热和 安逸
Warmer and warmer as you eat. Nice!
# 这油也差不多了
The oil is ready
# 先放花椒干辣椒
Put in Sichuan peppercorns and dry chili first
# 再放点姜蒜
And then ginger and garlic
# 都闻到香了
I can already smell the flavor
# 这个蒜下去了一定要面慢慢小火炒
Garlic must be fried slowly on low heat
# 把这个蒜炸香
Fry it until aromatic
# 这个火锅才香
Then the hot pot can be aromatic
# 一般我们这边吃火锅
Speaking of our local hot pot recipes,
# 花椒辣椒大蒜姜少不了
We can’t miss any of Sichuan peppercorn, chili, garlic or ginger
# 还有就是豆瓣酱
And also doubanjiang (aka broad bean chili paste)
# 这个辣椒慢慢变成褐色了
The chili is turning brown slowly
# 差不多了放点豆瓣酱
Alright, put in some doubanjiang
# 豆瓣酱的话就根据汤的量来算
The amount of doubanjiang depends on the amount of soup
# 也不能太多也不能太少
Neither too much, nor too little
# 要不然没味道
Otherwise it feels unflavorful
# 好 豆瓣酱炒香了就加这个火锅底料
Alright, the doubanjiang is aromatic. Add in hot pot soup base
# 好
Good
# 这里可能有2斤多
It should be more than 2 jin?
# 2斤倒是有的
Yeah, at least 2 jin
# 这个慢慢给它炒化
Let’s melt it slowly
# 这个就是上次我炒的火锅底料
This is the hot pot soup base I made last time
# 四伯爷你说这里面有没有5斤油
Uncle, do you think there are 5 jin of oil in the wok?
# 差不多 有5斤油
Should be. 5 jin of oil
# 5斤油的话我准备放3斤水
For 5 jin of oil, I’ll add 3 jin of water into it
# 好
Yeah
# 现在就等它慢慢熬着
Now let’s cook it slowly and wait
# 要得要得
Sure, sure
# 我给你打个料（蘸料）你吃辣点嘛不辣哦
I’ll make a dipping sauce for you. Do you want spicy or not?
# 唉呀 也不要很辣嘛
Eh-ya, not too spicy
# 我喜欢放点蒜
I’d like some garlic
# 然后这个小米辣
And this xiaomila chili pepper
# 花生碎
Chopped peanuts
# 花椒面
Ground Sichuan peppercorns
# 辣椒面
Chili powder
# 然后就是这个香油
And also sesame oil
# 香油要放得比较重一些
Need a bit more sesame oil
# 我个人口味是这样
That’s my own preference
# 再加一点蚝油
And also some oyster sauce
# 再放点葱
Some green onion
# 葱跟香菜最后放
Green onion and cilantro should be added at the end
# 有的人还可以放一点这个鸡精
Some people may also want to add a bit of chicken broth powder
# 鸡精的话少放一点
Don’t add too much
# 因为汤底里面都还要放
as we’ll season the soup base with it
# 四伯爷我给你打还是自己打
Uncle, would you like me or yourself to make it?
# 你打嘛
You make it
# 我打噶
I’ll make it
# 辣点嘛
Spicy?
# 可以可以辣点蒜多点
OK, OK. Spicy, and some more garlic
# 蒜多点 要得
More garlic, sure
# 可以了
Alright
# 鸡精要不要
Chicken broth powder?
# 可以可以
Sure
# 麻呢（花椒面）
Numbing? (Sichuan pepper powder)
# 麻点都不关事
Numbing is fine. Doesn’t matter (even if it’s very numbing)
# 葱花 香菜要不要
Chopped green onion and cilantro?
# 要 要少点
Yeah, a bit
# 香油
Sesame oil?
# 要要要
Yeah, yeah, yeah
# 好的
OK
# 蚝油要不要
Oyster sauce?
# 整点 整点
Yeah, a little
# 好 酱油要不要
OK. Soy sauce?
# 我的是没有放酱油的
I didn’t add soy sauce into mine
# 少放点嘛不是等会儿吃着吃着就咸了呢
Just a bit. Or it becomes more and more salty as I eat
# 少放点
Just a bit
# 好
OK
# 好 那我先把味调了多
Alright, I’ll season it first
# 放这么多冰糖要得不
I’m putting this much rock sugar. Is that OK?
# 要得要得
OK, OK
# 就稍微回甜点
For a slightly sweet aftertaste
# 要得
Sure
# 放点冰糖
A bit of rock sugar
# 再放点盐
And a bit of salt
# 好 就放这么多盐
Alright, just a little salt
# 农村就是这点好噶
That’s the good part about countryside
# 吃什么就到土头去扯（地里去摘）
Whatever you want to eat, just pull it out from the soil (pick in the fields)
# 是啊
Yeah
# 农村就有这么方便撒 再城市里还要去买
It’s so convenient in the countryside. In a city, you have to go out and buy
# 我尝一下汤看看
Let me try the soup
# 咸不咸
Salty or not?
# 不咸
Not salty
# （现在）不咸等会儿煮一会儿就咸了
Not salty now. It will become salty after boiling for a while
# 这次的刚好
It’s just about right
# 因为如果是淡了的话在那个
And if you find it not salty enough
# 蘸碟里面加盐加蚝油就可以了
just put some salt or oyster sauce in your dipping sauce
# 可以
Good!
# 要得
Well done!
# 差不多了四伯爷
It’s ready, uncle
# 我们坐到吃吗
Shall we sit here and eat?
# 吃嘛
Yeah
# 要得 板凳端过来坐到吃
Yeah, take the stools here
# 伯娘
Aunt?
# 坐到吃
Take a seat
# 要得
Alright
# 我们吃火锅一般先下这种不容易熟的
We first add the ingredients that takes longer to cook into the hot pot
# 先给它丢下去慢慢煮
Dump them in and take time to stew them
# 这个香菇可以煮很久
These shiitake mushrooms can be stewed for very long
# 煮很久都没关系
It doesn’t matter
# 先放点脑花下去煮
Cook some pig brains first
# 现在我四伯在拈黄鳝
Uncle is adding Asian swamp eels into the pot
# 这个黄鳝还很大哦
These eels are large
# 这个黄鳝我们夹的时候不要用自己的筷子去夹
When picking up Asian swamp eel, don’t use our own chopsticks
# 就怕自己误食了这个生黄鳝（血）
in case we eat raw eel (blood)
# 因为那个生黄鳝血是有毒的
Because raw eel blood is poisonous
# 先吃点毛肚嘛 四伯爷
Have some tripe, uncle?
# 要得呀
Sure thing
# 先整毛肚这种块点的
Have some fast cooking stuff like beef tripe
# 好好好
Yeah yeah yeah
# 一哈放下去
Put it in
# 好好好
Yeah yeah yeah
# 黄鳝都好了
The eels are ready
# 白菜
Cabbage
# 那我们这个就是大杂烩了哟 这样子
Now we are making a hodge-podge like this
# 放心大胆的吃四伯爷 好了的
Take it easy, uncle! They are ready to eat
# 香菇都好了
Even the mushrooms are ready
# 怕的是没好（熟）
I was afraid they are not cooked enough
# 没好（熟）的吃了不好
Eating not-cooked-enough is not good enough
# 诶呀 好嫩哦
Eh-ya, so tender
# 是不是哦
Really?
# 很嫩啊
So tender
# 比豆腐花都嫩
More tender than a tofu pudding
# 安逸
Nice
# 这个味道比上次的那个味道都还好吃
It tastes even better than last time
# 给你加了油的都嘛
We’ve added oil for you
# 安逸
Nice
# 来 伯娘
Here you are, aunt
# 好 谢谢
Oh, thanks
# 多拈点
Take more
# 来嘛 我拈点给你
Come on, it’s for you
# 这个可以
This is good
# 这个真的好吃
This is really delicious
# 所以我们学这个
So, if we learn things like
# 一些家常菜呀火锅呀
some home cooking dishes, or hot pot
# 学来反正东西是自己的
Everything’s still your own anyways
# 现在人家吃火锅还是便宜撒
Now it’s cheap for them to have hot pot
# 在网上订火锅底料定起回去
Order some soup base online
# 那就可以自己熬来干了撒
Then they can cook it and do it by themselves
# 来 四伯爷我把脑花给你漏起来
Uncle, I’ll scoop the pig brains for you
# 伯娘 来
Here you are, aunt
# 好了 给小芬
Alright, give some to Xiaofen
# 老婆
Honey
# 夹一个
Take one
# 这里还有一个
And another one here
# 我能吃那么多吗
Can I eat that many?
# 没问题
No problem
# 不要吃超过2-3个就可以了
Eating no more than 3 is fine
# 诶 这个
Hey, this one
# 你最喜欢吃的
Your favorite
# 金针菇
Enoki mushrooms
# 老婆香菇
Honey! Shiitake mushrooms
# 我要吃白菜
Can I get some cabbage?
# 白菜呀 好
Cabbage? Sure!
# 好啦本期视频就先到这里
Alright, that’s all for this episode
# 我这个口水都一直在流
I’ve been drooling all the time
# 少说话多吃菜
Talk less, eat more